Guide to the Propaganda Poster Collection 1914-1996
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 4: International Relations Propaganda Posters (United States and International),World War II, 1939-1945
  - War Savers "If", circa 1939-1945; English; 21 x 30.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Issued by the War Savings Committee. (Folder 55, Item 287)
    Pamphlet features a poem written by an English War Saver that is modeled after Rudyard Kipling's Poem of the same name. A British flag on a pole runs along the left border. (2 copies)
  - The United Nations Fight For Freedom, 1942; English; 25 x 35.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Graphics Division, Office of Facts and Figures, Washington D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 55, Item 288)
    Small poster issued by the Office of Facts and Figures showing the current members of the United Nations fighting alongside America. Graphic shows the flags of the United Nations with the Statue of Liberty situated among them.
  - An Open Letter to the Unconquerable Poles, circa 1939-1945; English; 29 x 37 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Poem by Joseph Auslander. Painting by Everett Henry. Published in the Saturday Evening Post. (Folder 55, Item 289)
    A poem written in honor of the resistance of the Polish people against the Nazis as they were invaded. Background painting shows a Polish man and woman standing amongst the rubble of their city with sunlight breaking through the distant clouds.
  - This man is your Friend (Ethiopian), 1942; English; 36 x 51 cm. Black and white with blue detail.; Creator/Publisher: Graphics Division, Office of Facts and Figures, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 55, Item 290)
    Poster issued by the Office of Facts and Figures to distinguish friend from foe by showing a picture of an Ethiopian soldier with the phrase, "He fights for Freedom."
  - This man is your Friend (Chinese), 1942; English; 36 x 51 cm. Black and white with blue detail.; Creator/Publisher: Graphics Division, Office of Facts and Figures, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 55, Item 291)
    Poster issued by the Office of Facts and Figures to distinguish friend from foe by showing a picture of a Chinese soldier with the phrase, "He fights for Freedom."
  - This man is your Friend (Dutch Sailor), 1942; English; 36 x 51 cm. Black and white with blue detail.; Creator/Publisher: Graphics Division, Office of Facts and Figures, Washington, D.C. U.S. Government Printing Office. (Folder 55, Item 292)
    Poster issued by the Office of Facts and Figures to distinguish friend from foe by showing a picture of a Dutch Sailor with the phrase, "He fights for Freedom."
  - Extracts From Adolf Hitler's Public Speeches, circa 1939-1945; English; 43 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unknown (Folder 55, Item 293)
    A collection of excerpts from Adolf Hitler's speeches from February 10, 1933 to September 1, 1939. Poster demonstrates the gradual change of Hitler's objectives as Europe begins to fall under attack by Nazi Germany.
  - Silence, l'Ennemi Guette Vos Confindences, 1939; French; 38.5 x 58 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Paul Colin. (Folder 55, Item 294)
    Poster issued by French government to help prevent the leak of confidential information to the enemy. Graphic shows cartoon depiction of two people sharing information with a large shadow leaning in. English Translation: "Silence, the enemy awaits your co
  - Yugoslav Guerrillas, The Second Front in Europe, circa 1942-1945; English; 45.5 x 56.5 cm. Black and white with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Leopoldo Méndez. (Folder 55, Item 295)
    Poster illustrated by Leopoldo Méndez showing Yugoslavians attacking Nazis with the main aggressor wielding an axe.
  - Two Years Ago The British Empire Stood Alone.., circa 1942; English; 48 x 63.5 cm. Black and white with red detail.; Creator/Publisher: British Information Services, 30 Rockefeller Plaza, New York City. (Folder 55, Item 296)
    Poster informing the public that while two years ago Britain stood alone, at this moment four-fifths of the world was united with them against the Axis powers. Graphic shows a soldier with a gun by his side standing on a field covered with barbed wire.
  - Men of Valor, They Fight For You, 1943; English; 60.5 x 91 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Hubert Rogers. Wartime Information Board, Ottawa, Printed in Canada. (Folder 55, Item 297)
    Poster issued by the Canadian government featuring an excerpt from citation awarding Victoria Cross to Lt.-Col. Merritt, South Saskatchewan Regt., Dieppe, on August 19, 1942. The quote tells of the heroic actions of a soldier who helped cover the withdraw
  - It's Got To Fit...To Do Its Bit!, circa 1939-1945; English; 61 x 91 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Issued by Wartime Information Board, Ottawa, for Department of Munitions and Supply. Printed in Canada. (Folder 55, Item 298)
    Canadian poster encouraging citizens to donate better quality of scrap materials than what can be found in the "scrap heap." Graphic shows a gear wheel following a track.
  - China, First to Fight!, circa 1941-1945; English; 68 x 104 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Martha Sawyers. Litho. in U.S.A. (Folder 55, Item 299)
    Poster issued by United China Relief to encourage American citizens to make contributions to the National War Fund in support of Chinese allies in need.
- Series 5: French Posters
  - Subseries 5.1: French World War II, 1939-1945
    - Notre Immortelle Marseillaise, circa 1939-1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 56, Item 300)
      Propaganda poster featuring a female warrior (Marianne figure) highlighted with a red and blue backdrop.
    - Liberte Egale Pour Tous, circa 1939-1945; French; 76.5 x 111.5 cm. Blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 56, Item 301)
      Poster with a graphic in the upper left of a boy writing at a desk.
    - Journee Internationale des Femmes, circa 1945; French; 79 x 119 cm. Red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Union of French Women. (Folder 56, Item 302)
      Propaganda poster announcing the meeting of delegates from England, United States, Soviet Union, and France.
    - Pour Les Soldats, circa 1939-1945; French; 72.5 x 114.5 cm. Red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: The National Committee of C. D. H. (Folder 56, Item 303)
      Propaganda poster featuring a graphic of three goods needed to help soldiers fighting on the front: cigarettes, textiles, and money.
    - Au Peuple de Paris, circa 1939-1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: The Committee of the Liberation of Paris. (Folder 56, Item 304)
      Public announcement to the people of Paris about the state of the war. Includes two stripes in upper left-hand corner, one red and the other blue.
    - Grand Gala, circa 1939-1945; French; 80.5 x 120 cm. Red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Chaix. (Folder 56, Item 305)
      Announcement of a grand gala under the Minister of Public Works and Transport.
    - Les Armees Alliees Marchent sur Berlin, circa 1945; French; 79.5 x 119.5 cm. Red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: France-U. R. S. S. Association. (Folder 56, Item 306)
      Propaganda poster featuring a message about Allied armies marching on Berlin, as well as a request for individuals to join the France-U.R.S.S. Association.
    - Il Faut Finir Rapidement la Fuerre!, circa 1939-1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Union of Labor Unions of the Paris Region. (Folder 57, Item 307)
      Propaganda poster explaining the necessity that France finishes the war.
    - Appel a l'Opinion Publique at aux du Nazisme: Ils ont des droits sur nous, circa 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Black and red text with a red and blue border.; Creator/Publisher: National Association of Victims of Nazism. (Folder 57, Item 308)
      Propaganda poster presenting statements from the National Association of Victims of Nazism.
    - [Marshal Petain's Speech], 1941; French; 80 x 120 cm. Black and red text with red and blue border.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 57, Item 309)
      Poster featuring two hexagonal graphics in red, blue, and black with the words "1er Mai, Fête National du Travail" along the perimeter. The top image depicts a labrys (two-sided ax) and the bottom image portrays lilies crossed with another flower. Poster
    - [Aid Provided by the French Red Cross], circa 1939-1945; French; 79.5 x 115 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 57, Item 310)
      Propaganda poster depicting an arrow pointing from an image of a village to a camp, surrounded by illustrations of people, books, board games, musical instruments, and a map of France.
    - Les Boches Sont Passes la!, circa 1944; French; 84.5 x 124 cm. Blue text and images.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 57, Item 311)
      Propaganda poster featuring two images of the remains from the destruction of the village Oradour sur Glane.
    - Le Drapeau de la Liberte Flotte sur Berlin!, circa 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Purple background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 57, Item 312)
      Announcement to the people of Paris with information about Berlin and Joseph Stalin.
    - La Confederation Generale du Travail parle aux Travailleurs, circa 1945-1949; French; 80 x 120 cm. Red and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Office of the General Confederation of Labor. (Folder 57, Item 313)
      Propaganda poster from the Office of the General Confederation of Labor.
    - Preparez une Nouvelle Floraison de l'Esprit Francais en Participant a la Fondation de l'Encyclopedie de la Renaissance Francaise., circa 1945; French; 80 x 119.5 cm. Red and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 58, Item 314)
      Poster listing contributors and requesting participants for the foundation of the Encyclopedia of the French Renaissance.
    - Les Conditions de la Renaissance Francaise, circa 1945; French; 80 x 118 cm. Red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 58, Item 315)
      Propaganda poster explaining the conditions of the French Renaissance.
    - Grande Soiree de Bienfaisance au Profit des Oeuvres Sociales de 'C.D.L.R.' 'Ceux De La Resistance' et des Blesses des Invalides, circa 1945; French; 82 x108 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: H. Dieval. (Folder 58, Item 316)
      An advertisement for an event held for the benefit of social work organizations. Includes two stripes in upper left corner and two in the bottom right, one red and the other blue.
    - 1er Congres National de l'Union des Femmes Francaises: Gde Manifestation Feminine Artistique, circa 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Blue and red text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 58, Item 317)
      Announcement for the first National Congress of the Union of French Women. Includes two prints.
    - [Grand Event Announcement], circa 1939-1945; French; 84.5 x 122 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: The National Association of Victims of Nazism. (Folder 58, Item 318)
      Poster publicizing a grand evening event to be organized by the National Association of Victims of Nazism. Lists speakers and entertainers for the program.
    - Remise de Points Textiles Chiffons, Vetements Usages et tous Dechets de Provenance Domestique, 1943; French; 80 x 120 cm. Black and red text.; Creator/Publisher: Ministry of Industrial Production and Communications. (Folder 58, Item 319)
      Propaganda poster featuring a list of centers in the Seine-et-Oise department for the exchange of textiles.
    - [French Red Cross Encouraging Packages for Soldiers], circa 1939-1945; French; 80 x 118.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Red Cross. (Folder 59, Item 320)
      Propaganda poster with a graphic of a woman and two children at home while a soldier opens a package of goods received from home.
    - [Learning German], 1943; French; 59.5 x 79.5 cm. Black and red text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 59, Item 321)
      French poster encouraging people to enroll in a German language course. Includes a mixture of cursive decorative text and bolded block text.
    - Paysan de France!, circa 1939-1945; French; 55 x 74.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 59, Item 322)
      Poster directed toward French peasants and their protests.
    - Union des Femmes de Prisonniers, circa 1939-1945; French; 57 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 59, Item 323)
      Propaganda poster depicting two women joining hands in the shadows of two men.
    - Exposition des Oeuvres des Invalides, 1942; 59.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Ch. Vilers. (Folder 59, Item 324)
      Features a person in poor health presenting a wooden boat with a red cross on its sail.
    - Conserves Familiales, circa 1939-1945; French; 59.5 x 40 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 59, Item 325)
      Propaganda poster supporting the preservation of family in the Centre de Palaiseau.
    - Quinzaine des Enfants de Deportes et Fusilles, circa 1939-1945; French; 56 x 80 cm. Brown text and image.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 59, Item 326)
      Depicts the image of a young child transfixed by something located above it.
    - [Renovation for Parisians], circa 1939-1945; French; 56 x 86 cm. Black and white with blue accent.; Creator/Publisher: Republican Party of Renovation. (Folder 60, Item 327)
      French poster alerting Parisians about the Republican Party of Renovation. Includes a single blue stripe in the top left-hand corner.
    - Union et Action., circa 1945; French; 58.5 x 82 cm. Red and blue text with a colored image.; Creator/Publisher: Speciale du F. P. J. (Folder 60, Item 328s1)
      Propaganda poster featuring three figures; two men clasping hands, one in a blue uniform, the other in white, and a woman dressed in red. All three figures appear to be in action and moving in a forward motion.
    - La Guerre Continue...pour Noel a tous un Colis, circa 1945; French; 58.5 x 82 cm. Red, blue, and black text with a black and white image.; Creator/Publisher: Speciale du F. P. J. (Folder 60, Item 328s2)
      Poster illustrating three soldiers on the frontline of battle receiving Christmas packages.
    - Vive la France, circa 1939-1945; French; 24 x 112.5 cm. Blue text on a white background with a red border.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 60, Item 329)
      Propaganda poster in red, blue, and white, reading Vive la France.
    - Revision et Etablissement des Listes Electorales, 1944; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 60, Item 330)
      Features information on the establishment and revision of the electoral lists, including the corresponding dates for persons based upon the first letter of their name.
    - La Republique en Peril, 1945; French; 58.5 x 79.5 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 60, Item 331)
      The announcement of a grand meeting to be held on May 29, 1945 to discuss the perilous state of the republic.
    - Scandales et Provocations, circa 1939-1945; French; 79 x 59 cm. (each part). Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 60, Item 332)
      Propaganda poster directed toward workers, consumers, merchants, and housewives about scandals and provocations in France. Split between two sheets of paper.
    - 1er Congres du Front National de l'Ile de France, circa 1939-1945; French; 118.5 x 38.5 cm. Blue background with red and white text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 60, Item 333)
      French poster that focuses on the text, Front National, with the use of contrasting colors. The dates and location of the congress are emphasized within a black border.
    - Electeurs, Electrices du VI Arrondissement, circa 1944; French; 59.5 x 90 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 61, Item 334)
      Propaganda poster presenting a list of intentions for electors and voters to view, with the purpose of assisting France's war effort. Consists of two strips on both the top and bottom of the poster, one red and the other blue.
    - [Tenant Housing and Policy], circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Federation of Tenants of the Paris Region. (Folder 61, Item 335)
      Propaganda poster depicting appeals made by the Federation of Tenants of the Paris Region toward the people and government of France.
    - Femmes, Lisez Ceci, circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. Purple background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 61, Item 336)
      A poster directed toward women, featuring statements about their duty in the war.
    - Commercants! Artisans!, circa 1945; French; 100 x 65.5 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 61, Item 337)
      Propaganda poster drawing the attention of merchants and artisans, informing them about a grand meeting organized by the French Communist Party.
    - Sabotage de l'Effort de Guerre: les 3 Officiers de Maubeuge, circa 1945; French; 65.5 x 102 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Committee for the Liberation of Officers of Maubeuge. (Folder 61, Item 338)
      Propaganda poster depicting an announcement about three officers of Maubeuge who are heroes of the Resistance in France.
    - Femmes!: le Parti Communiste Francais s'Adressera Particuliement a vous par la voix de son Secretaire General Maurice Thorez, circa 1945; French; 100 x 65 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 61, Item 339)
      Propaganda poster publicizing the Secretary General Maurice Thorez's speech directed toward women. The date and location of the event are emphasized with a black backdrop.
    - Tout pour le Front!! Tout pour la Victoire!!, 1945; French; 55.5 x 76 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Henri Delvert. (Folder 61, Item 340)
      Announcement of the date, time, and location of a meeting aimed to eradicate the Hitlerism of Germany and return prisoners and deportees to France.
    - Contre l'Augmentation de 50% du Prix des Loyers pour la Securite de Votre Foyer, circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. Pink background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Federation of Tenants and Users of Gas and Electricity in the Paris Region. (Folder 62, Item 341)
      Propaganda poster addressing the issue of increased amounts in rent payments.
    - Parisiens...le Parti Socialiste vous Parlera le Jeudi 5 Avril, a 20 Heures 30, circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Socialist Federation of the Seine. (Folder 62, Item 342s1)
      Propaganda poster featuring the date, time, and location of a speech held by the Socialist Party.
    - Pour la Liberation Politique et Sociale, circa 1939-1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. Red, black, and white.; Creator/Publisher: Socialist Party. (Folder 62, Item 342s2)
      Propaganda poster presenting a program discussing political and social liberation.
    - Le Marche Noir: Cancer du Ravitaillement, circa 1945; French; 64 x 93 cm. White background with red and black text and graphic.; Creator/Publisher: National Front. (Folder 62, Item 343)
      Features a graphic of a piece of meat, a loaf of bread, and a package, all surrounded by the red outline of a crab (cancer).
    - Secours Nationa: ils ont Froid ils ont Faim Aidez-Moi a les Secourir, 1940-1944 circa; French; 61.5 x 100.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: J. E. Goossens. (Folder 62, Item 344)
      Propaganda poster with an enlarged photograph of Marshal Petain and a red graphic of women and children grouped together against his heart.
    - Les Hommes des Trusts ont Trahi! Qu'ils Soient Chatis! Que Tous Leurs Biens Soient Confisqus!, 1945; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 62, Item 345)
      Graphic of a magnifying glass enlarging texts from the newspaper Journal de la Bourse. Located in the lower right-hand side of the poster is a small image of a helmet detailed with a blue circle and a red outer circle. The back of the poster depicts a po
    - Le Havre est Detruit!, 1939-1945 circa; French; 80.5 x 55.5 cm. (each part). White background with black and red text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 62, Item 346)
      Propaganda poster announcing the destruction of buildings and the demand for rebuilding. Split between two sheets of paper.
    - Guerre aux Trusts: le Parti Socialiste vous Appelle au Combat, circa 1939-1945; French; 59 x 79.5 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Socialist Party S.F.I.O. (French Section of the Workers' International). (Folder 62, Item 347)
      Propaganda poster featuring a Socialist Party request for individuals to fight in the war on trusts.
    - Appel Officiers et Sous-Officiers de Reserve, circa 1939-1945; French; 56 x 45 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 63, Item 348)
      Propaganda poster announcing a call for officers and noncommissioned officers of the reserve. Text is bordered with red and blue lines.
    - Accueillons Dignement ceux qui Reviennent d'Allemagne!, circa 1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L. Hannequin. (Folder 63, Item 349)
      Declaration that the people of France accept with dignity those returning from Germany.
    - L'oural Arsenal de l'Armee Rouge, circa 1939-1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Blue background with black and white text and image.; Creator/Publisher: Curial-Archereau. (Folder 63, Item 350)
      Propaganda poster featuring a photograph of an industrial building against a blue background.
    - Meeting pour le Ravitaillement, circa 1939-1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: Local Committee of Liberation. (Folder 63, Item 351)
      Propaganda poster publicizing a meeting to be held by the Local Committee of Liberation. Includes two stripes in upper left-hand corner, one red and the other blue.
    - Jeunesse Francais: Libre, circa 1939-1945; French; 58.5 x 80 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 63, Item 352)
      Propaganda poster requesting the youths of France to participate in the war effort. Depicted in the upper left-hand corner is a symbol above the letters "JFL" within an outline of France. Includes a border of interlacing red and blue lines.
    - Jeunes Gens, Jeunes Filles de la Region Parisienne, circa 1939-1945; French; 59 x 84 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Nouvelle. (Folder 63, Item 353)
      Propaganda poster directed toward young men and girls of the Paris region.
    - Principes de la Communaute, 1943; French; 65 x 100 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: B. Arnaud. (Folder 63, Item 354)
      Lists the sixteen Principles of the Community. Includes a decorative red and blue border and two identical graphics of a red, white, and blue labrys (two-sided ax) with five stars located above and below the list.
    - La Releve Continue!, 1942; French; 79 x 116 cm. Black and white photograph with blue text and accents.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 64, Item 355)
      Propaganda poster showing an image of a train carriage, filled with French infantryman waving through the open windows. Main body of text is placed within a blue square with rounded corners.
    - Les Prisonniers Rapatries du Canton de Remalard: vous Invitent a deux Representations "Comme au Camp", circa 1939-1945; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 64, Item 356)